<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[An Unexpected Coder]]></title>
  <link href="http://ccmeyers.github.io/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://ccmeyers.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2014-06-12T09:25:38-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://ccmeyers.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Catherine Meyers]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Surprising Accessibility of Coding]]></title>
    <link href="http://ccmeyers.github.io/blog/2014/06/11/first-post-6-dot-11-dot-14/"/>
    <updated>2014-06-11T23:44:16-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://ccmeyers.github.io/blog/2014/06/11/first-post-6-dot-11-dot-14</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>If you had come up to me a year ago and told me that I would become a web developer, I would have laughed in your face…hard. But here I am, after having a career as a professional opera singer, learning Ruby, a back-end web programming language used to develop some pretty complex web applications. And I’m actually liking it.</p>

<p>
Like many, when I thought of programming, a stereo-type came to mind: one of a socially awkward loner whose brain works at lightning speed and is most likely a genius at math. And when I decided to switch careers at 30, I never thought of coding as a possibility. I was after all, coming from the world of opera. Opera singer turned coder? Ha! But then, at the urging of multiple friends, I decided to give it a chance. 
</p>


<p>
What I discovered was that I was completely wrong about coding. It isn’t just for rocket-scientists and math geniuses. Not to say it isn’t hard. It is. I’m working my ass off. But I found it isn’t this unachievable thing that only people very far-removed from me can accomplish.
</p>


<p>
I quickly discovered, that I already had skills that are applicable to coding. Programming languages are just that, languages. And more and more, these languages are being developed to mimic the english language. Ruby is a great example of this. Want the word “Hello” to appear on your computer screen? Code in “puts ‘Hello’”. That makes a lot more sense than you thought it would, doesn’t it? Of course, it gets way more complicated than that. But it’s a great example of how learning a programming language is just learning new vocabulary within a new syntax. Anyone who has spent time learning a foreign language, already has experience with this. 
</p>


<p>
I was also surprised by the creativity involved in coding. It isn’t just writing a bunch of zeros and ones that will sit on a server all alone like a chubby girl at a school dance. It’s building something that will speak to the world and could even change someone’s life…or just let them buy shoes, which is also cool. There are a million different ways, especially in Ruby, that allow you to code the same thing. You have a lot more freedom than you think and this is where you can let your creativity flow.
</p>


<p>
In the future, most of my blog posts will be more technical, focusing on specific aspects of Ruby and coding in general. But I thought it was so important to address this huge misconception the majority of humanity has when it comes to this profession. I urge you take a stab at it. Try your hand at HTML at <a href="http://code.org">code.org</a> or <a href="http://www.codecademy.com">codecademy</a>. Or, if you are an experienced coder who wants to help make coding more accessible to more people, volunteer for such non-profits as <a href="http://girlswhocode.com">Girls Who Code</a> or <a href="http://www.coderdojonyc.com">CoderDojo NYC</a> and help spread the code.
</p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
